[Music]
this is fortress on a hill with Henry
Danny Kagan and
[Music]
joanni well welcome everybody to
fortress on a hill a podcast about US
foreign policy
anti-imperialism skepticism and the
American way of War I'm Henry thank you
for joining us today with me is a very
special guest somebody we wanted to talk
to for for quite a while um the the the
myth the man the legend Mr John
kiraku um and uh we're going to get to
chat with him for a while and you know
uh hear about some of his experiences
many
experiences um for anybody who doesn't
know uh John kyaku was a former CIA
counterterrorism officer and a former
senior investigator with the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee uh John
became the sixth whistleblower indicted
by the Obama Administration under the
Espionage Act a law designed to punish
spies he served 23 months in prison as
the result of his attempts to oppose the
bush administration's torture program
John welcome to fortress on Hill thanks
for having
me so I I'd um I'd like to give the
listeners kind of a sense of um your
your overall background certainly we
don't have to go in everything into into
great detail but I'd like to to hear a
bit about your career about um how you
came to the point that you became a a
whistleblower and
um what how you see that career now
today looking back on
it sure the second part of the uh of the
question is the more difficult one the
the easier part is I was recruited into
the CIA when I was in graduate school at
uh George Washington
University I uh I had an advisor a
professor whom I respected very deeply
uh and and I continued to respect until
until he died uh that was Dr Gerald post
he recruited me into the CIA my second
year in grad school and um I started at
the CIA the first week of January 1990
as an analyst on Iraq and
um uh spent the first seven and a half
years of my career working exclusively
on Iraq including tour overseas in the
Middle East working Iraqi sanctions
issues I was in an office at the CIA
that no longer exists it's called it was
called the office of leadership analysis
so my job really was to be Saddam
Hussein's classified biographer or his
biographer for the intelligence
Community I got bored with that after
seven seven and a half years and so I
made a very unusual switch to
counterterrorism operations because at
the time um I was the only person quite
literally I was the only person in the
CIA who was fluent in both Greek and
Arabic so uh they sent me to Athens as
the um counterterrorism
representative um mostly covering Arab
terrorism abun nidal organization pflp
dflp
ppgc all those old school communist uh
and nationalist terrorist groups and a
Greek group called revolutionary
organization 17
November I did that until uh the summer
of 2000 and then went back to
headquarters I was I was uh working um I
have to be careful of my language I was
I was training Middle Eastern
intelligence services and
counterterrorism operations and then 911
hit and uh I was named um the chief of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
after 911
um in that job I led a series of raids
that resulted in the capture of Abu
zubeda who we believed at the time was
the number three in al-Qaeda he wasn't
and um went back to headquarters on the
strength of the Abu zua capture I got
promoted to uh executive assistant to
the cia's deputy director and
um and then my final tour was at the
United Nations in New York and I
resigned from from New York to go into
the private sector and then later back
into government at the Senate Foreign
Relations
Committee um I'm curious about your time
working and and again I like you said
I'm real careful about what you what you
can share but the time working on Iraqi
sanctions
um uh I'm curious about especially about
that time because it it you know it in
some ways it informs the state of Iraq
to today almost as much as the Iraq War
does um but is there is there anything
that you can share with us about about
that time just kind of the you know the
maybe your overall impressions of it
yeah it was it was that long period of
Iraqi sanctions that convinced me that
well number one sanctions don't work
sure and number two they
are cruel to the point of becoming in
many cases
crimes against humanity you know I
remember in the very beginning of the
sanctions regime beginning in August of
1990 um the state department of the
White
House took very seriously the notion
that the Iraqi people needed to continue
receiving food and Medicine okay so so
they they wrote up a un Security Council
resolution
986 and then the Iraqi said well we need
you know these pipes right for our sewer
system we can't deliver clean water
without these pipes well then the CIA
says wait a minute those kinds of pipes
are used in South Africa to run fiber
optic cable and you can use fiber optic
cable for a weapons of mass destruction
program so no pipes well with no pipes
then you get no clean water and when you
get no clean water people start to get
sick and then and the US government says
well you know they shouldn't be using
this much uh in uh antibiotics they must
be doing something with the antibiotics
they're making a BW program out of it
and the next thing you
know thousands tens of thousands of
people mostly children are dying and
they're dying as a direct result of
these
sanctions and I remember a senior
officer telling
me sanctions are always a bad idea
because they never do anything to the
person being targeted Saddam Hussein
didn't give a [__] about sanctions no
right he had a very sophisticated
sanctions busting regime set up at the
American em or at the Iraqi Embassy in
Aman Jordan he had a a cousin who was in
charge of it at the time and so it was
only the Iraqi people and when I say the
Iraqi people I mean the Innocence among
the Iraqi people women children
minorities you know Kurds Shia they were
the ones who were suffering it wasn't
Saddam or his TTI Clan or his alja
family or really any sunnis in the in
the power structure of the Iraqi
government and Military none of them
suffered at all from sanctions the Iraqi
people suffered from
sanctions uh you know we renewed
sanctions so many times after 986 it was
1096 and then it was like 1234 and it
was just year after year after year
sanctions were being were being renewed
and I remember saying to a colleague of
mine a buddy of mine at the
time I can't do this as a
career nothing's going to change
American policies not going to change
and we're not serious about taking out
Saddam nor should we have been because
that in and of itself would have been a
violation of international law as it was
later um but I just decided I I had to
do something different and more
interesting and every let me tell you
every Greek American at the CIA all
through the cia's history has wanted to
serve in Athens and so that's what we
all sought to do and I ended up getting
a great tour there I remember speaking
to um I did I did two tours in Iraq as a
as an Army MP and I remember speaking to
different people it was usually TR the
translators that we had because it was
easier for us to to go back and forth
but talking about just that entire ire
period and both you know the Gulf War in
and of itself the um the massive
killings that happened to those who rose
up against Saddam following George
Bush's call and that was one this this
particular guy I'm thinking of that that
was a huge thing for him but then and
then you know children dead children you
know from no food from no medicine sure
but in terms of trying to understand you
know the the the totality of American
involvement in Iraq and the costs that
had been paid and I I I read your uh
your recent article at Consortium news
regarding Tony blinkin pursuing Soviet
type weapons for use in Ukraine and how
Cyprus is still punished by the US for
refusing a similar request you know
understanding the place that that
Cypress had in that in terms of being
stuck they were certainly weren't
sanctioned but they were still being
punished in a very specific way for and
far as I can just not Towing the
American line it just by by just pushing
back as however however minorly they
did that's the exception to the rule you
know the only reason the cypriots have
the great life and the great country and
great economy and and honest democratic
government that they have is because
they're are Western for all intents and
purposes they're a Western Country but
you're right and 99 .9% of Americans
have no idea that we've had a weapons
embargo on Cyprus for the last 46
years 46 years sanctions on Cyprus of
all places now thank goodness that the
likes of the British and the French
thought that was ridiculous and that the
cypriots deserved an opportunity to
protect themselves against Turkish
expansionism because God knows the
Americans never came through we did an
episode a few months ago on fuia just
the history of the city as it pertained
to the Iraq War specifically regarding
the deaths of the American mercenaries
in fuia in March of 04 Iraqi citizens
were asked some polling questions
specifically about this Ambush why do
you think this happened is there
anything that you can point to and the
Iraqis were very pointed in response
that they knew the CIA had a long
history in Iraq from a multitude of
incidents and felt very strongly that
these black water mercenaries these
plain clothed contractors could have
been members of the CIA and that they
were there to commit acts of violence to
violate Iraqi sovereignty as it had been
many times before now understanding the
long section of US history on Iraq I I
don't know that you would want to call
them wrong you know in terms of having
that fear of not knowing and of course
they're not told they didn't get told
anything about what's actually happening
in their country why the United States
has chosen to keep this regime even you
know we're now more than a decade past
the official end of the Iraq War and
none of that has really changed I'm I'm
curious about because you worked on Iraq
for for such a long period of time and
it was uh you know in terms of you know
dealing with war on terror and other
things that how how do you see places
like that ever getting back to anything
that might seem normal yeah that's a
good question and I I think the very sad
answer is that they don't get back to
normal
look look at the US intervention in Iran
in the
1950s here we are 70 years later 70
years after we overthrew that government
and our relations still haven't returned
to normal we're still suffering from
that terrible foreign policy decision
you know one of the things that struck
me post 9911 on Iraq I I was intimately
involved in the planning for the Iraq
War I go into great detail about this in
my first book
and um one of the things that really
struck me was how these very important
people at the white house uh and in the
the power structure at the Pentagon knew
literally nothing about Iraqi history
about Iraqi culture and
Society I remember participating in a
secure video
teleconference where one of the Deputy
directors of the National Security
Council said and this was the day before
we crossed the Iraqi border he said when
we cross that border tomorrow they're
going to throw flowers at us and I
turned to my boss and I said was that a
joke or did they really know nothing
about Iraq and the answer I'm sorry to
say was that they knew
[Music]
nothing thing to look back at and
especially like you know
to you know I I I I realize looking at
this scope of it you know that the you
know I was an MP I was doing you know
ground stuff we were training the Iraqi
police and and in terms of but the but
once you understand the full breadth of
the history you know you may have played
and I mean you in the Royal sense you
know we we may have played a very small
role but we're still part of that giant
snowball that has crushed that country
that has been been a part of
that um so I'd like to move on to talk a
little bit about um whistleblowers and
specifically about uh Communications
management uh units um that's been
something that I've I've been reading
about for quite a while I I um but I I
saw your your blog post on your substack
and it it got me kind of thinking about
it again um I was wondering if you could
give our listeners kind of a a little
Basics on Communications management
units yeah so Communications management
units are specialized units inside the
US Federal prison system there are two
of them one is in the federal
penitentiary at Terra Hood Indiana it
used to be Federal death row they built
a new death row and then made the old
death row into a CMU the other
Communications management unit is at the
supermax prison in Marian Illinois now
the whole purpose of creating a a a
Communications management unit those are
important three important words that is
a a unit ins the most secure prisons in
America where all communication with the
outside world can be controlled right so
you have Omar abdurahman the the blind
shikh who's now dead you don't want him
communicating with people on the outside
so he can plan additional terrorist
attacks right so you want him to be cut
off we have the the last surviving Abu
nidal organization hijacker from the 19
uh 80s he's in the communications
management unit John Gotti uh the the
boss of the gambino crime family died in
a Communications management unit so
these things were set up for the worst
of the worst the most dangerous
prisoners people who had to be where the
American people had to be protected by
uh from them right but that's not really
what they are uh they're used to silence
people whose messages are inconvenient
for the government and so you've got a
Communications management
unit uh now that houses U Daniel hail
the Drone whistleblower and Daniel in my
view is a Bonafide American hero he's
the one that told the American people
that the that the Drone program run by
whomever DOD CIA NSC whoever happens to
be pulling the trigger on on any given
day was responsible for an 80% death
rate among
civilians okay well if it's a drone
program and it's be supposed to be so
much
safer right then why are 80% of the
people you kill civilians they're
accidental deaths he's the one that told
us about that now he was sentenced not
to 20 or 30 or 50 years in prison he was
sentenced to 42 months
which you know with time off for good
behavior is under three
years so if he's like so not dangerous
that he gets a prison sentence of less
than three years why in the world is he
a Communications management
unit because the justice department was
upset with the shortness of his sentence
another one is Marty
goddessi Marty go godd isfeld um was a
computer hacker and he read read an
article about a a little girl named
Justina uh in uh New England who was
born with a genetic disorder her parents
took her to Children's Hospital in
Boston uh after their doctor said look
we can't help her anymore in our little
town you should take her to Children's
in Boston the physicians at at
Children's Hospital in Boston said oh
she doesn't have this genetic disorder
uh she's being abused and starved by her
parents so They seized this girl they
arrested the
parents and then a year later they're
likeoh you know what she actually does
have this disorder uh our bad sorry you
can release the parents now and give
them their other two kids back so in
order to feel like he was helping Marty
initiated a a directed denial of service
attack on the Children's Hospital
fundraising website on the weekend of
its annual
fundraiser okay Not only was that worth
10 years in a maximum security
penitentiary and $2 million in in
reparations to children's hospital but
they put him in a
CMU now do we really need to be
protected from Marty goddessi that he's
so dangerous that we need to be we need
to have him locked away you know forever
well Marty gets out in two years and
he's going to go back home to Boston and
live happily ever after there's no
reason to have him in a Communications
management unit another one I just got
an email from him today is Donald
Reynolds Donald
Reynolds is in a
CMU serving a sentence of triple life
without parole for a a first time
nonviolent offense related to The Fast
and Furious Scandal now the reason he
got triple life without parole is
because he kept turning down the Justice
Department's offers for lighter
sentences because he said I didn't break
the law so why would I take a plea if I
didn't break the law okay you don't want
to take a plea not only are we going to
give you triple life without
parole but you're going to spend the
rest of your days in a Communications
management unit with no human contact
for the rest of your life and that's
what they did to them so these cmus
These are you know the United Nations
has already declared these cmus to be
forms of
torture right they're forms of torture
they're cruel and unusual
punishment and we we use them anyway and
it's worse than it's worse than just
having your Communications uh blocked or
banned you are locked 23 hours a day in
a 6x10 foot concrete cell everything's
made out of either concrete or steel uh
no windows that one hour a day you're
allowed to go out through a little door
it's about five feet high and you duck
down and you go out this little door
which opens up into a cage on the
outside like a dog cage and you can walk
in circles for an hour each day and then
you go back into your cell if you
receive mail you can't actually
physically hold the mail or receive it
they project your mail on a on a TV
monitor up at the ceiling so it's so
high up you can't touch it so you can't
like break it and you know take the
glass and cut your throat or something
they'll leave the mail available for you
for five minutes and then they take it
down and it's gone no TV no radio no
phone you're allowed one call a month
but it it's only to your attorney you
can't call your wife your kids your
friends nothing just your
attorney and that's where we put you
know some of the most important
whistleblowers that we
have I'm curious the large number of
whistleblowers that had come forward in
the post 911 global war on terror era
that why do you think um you know why
did the war on terror and the war on
whistleblowers coincide and why do you
think so many of them have been produced
by the same the same circumstances yeah
I can I can give you a very clear answer
to that um and that
was that was uh John
Brennan so there there have always been
whistleblowers through Modern American
history
um post 911 they became particularly
newsworthy right and um the George W
Bush
Administration
initiated Criminal investigations of two
whistleblowers uh Tom Drake from NSA and
Jeffrey Sterling from CIA but it was the
Obama
Administration that just launched an
allout open War on whistleblowers that's
because of John Brennan John Brennan
became the deputy National Security
adviser for counterterrorism in Obama's
first term and he became CIA director in
Obama's second term John Brennan had
nixonian obsession with National
Security leaks and it was John Brennan
Who convinced Barack Obama to use the
Antiquated Espionage Act as a cudel as
an iron
fist to to crush whistleblowers a New
York Times journalist told me that on
the day of my
arrest every single one of the New York
Times National Security sources went
silent and they stayed silent for six
months well that was the point of
Prosecuting me and Prosecuting seven
other whistleblowers uh during the Obama
Administration it wasn't necessarily to
teach John kyaku a lesson frankly they
made me
famous right they elevated me to this
position of like National human rights
spokesman anti-torture spokesman they
made me famous they they opened uh doors
and created opportunities for me that I
otherwise never would have had I would
be I would be wrapping up a career in
some cubicle somewhere if they hadn't uh
ordered my
arrest uh in in a funny way I'm kind of
glad they did because I think I've I've
done a lot more important work because
of my
arrest um and I want to say something
about the uh the Espionage Act too Henry
I think I think the Espionage Act is
very important it's something that
Americans really need to know about
the Espionage Act was written in 1917
passed into law in 1917 to combat German
sabots during the first World
War uh it was used right after passage
to to
incarcerate people who were opposed to
us entry into the war um most famously
Eugene V Debs the head of the Socialist
Party he actually ran for president from
his prison cell uh at the at the maximum
security penitentiary in Atlanta uh a
Hollywood producer was arrested and
charged with Espionage and served five
years because a movie that he made was
deemed to be not pro British enough
during World War I so
between
1917 and January of
2009 three Americans were charged with
Espionage for speaking speaking to the
media three Americans were charged with
Espionage for speaking to the media
between 1917 and
2019 in just the eight years of the
Obama presidency eight of us were
charged with Espionage for speaking to
the media and then under Donald Trump
another four were charged with Espionage
and you know beginning with with
me the sentences got longer and longer
and longer for each person after me I
was sitting with Tom Drake in Daniel
hail's uh sentencing hearing a year ago
October and um much to my shock my name
came up in
sentencing and uh the prosecution said
that they wanted I think they were
asking for 40 years in prison for Daniel
and Daniel's attorney said that they
were asking
for the same sentence that kiraku got I
got 30 months I served 23 and then the
judge said that Jeffrey Sterling got
kiraku plus 12 months because Jeffrey
Sterling went to
trial and then the judge said that he's
gone over the numbers and he's gon to
give Daniel kiraku plus 16
months and I'm just sitting there and
and I'm sitting like I'm sitting with
Tom Drake and then immediately in front
of me are three journalists from The
Washington Post the New York Times and
Politico and they were like you care to
comment and I said yeah he should have
been he should have been released you
know with with time served he doesn't
belong in prison we should be making
statues to people like him not sending
them to Communications management units
to make matters
worse um the judge recommended very
strongly in that sentencing hearing that
Daniel be sent to the low security
prison in uh Butner North Carolina he
has a substance abuse problem problem
and the Federal Bureau of Prisons has
this program called ardap the
residential drug and alcohol program and
if you go through arap which is
basically just sitting and watching
episodes of intervention and I mean that
quite quite literally that's that's what
our dap is and they say you know drugs
don't do them now watch this episode of
intervention and when you watch the
whole whatever it is 20 episodes you get
a year off your
sentence so I said to Daniel before you
went to prison listen this 42 months
this is a victory because you get 15%
off for good
behavior and then you get another year
off for art app I said and you're in a
low security prison you're just going to
lay there and read books and watch TV
and you're going to be home before you
know
it instead they sent him to the maximum
security penitentiary at Maran Illinois
and then put him in the CMU on top of
that which makes him ineligible for our
deap so he's going to do the whole 42
months even even with with good behavior
time that do they do they CTA that for
people in cmus well they they'll they
technically calculate it for people in
cmus but Marty godess Feld has already
lost all of his good behavior time
because he did terrible terrible things
like write a letter to a
journalist right like God
forbid and then in in a phone call to
his attorney he asked the attorney would
you call my wife and tell her that I'm
okay oh that's a third party
communication we're taking away all of
your good behavior
time so it's tough they do it on
purpose you know in my own sentencing
the the judge um ordered that i' be sent
to a minimum security Work Camp and in a
minimum security Camp there are no there
are no fences no bars on the windows the
doors are never locked you work in town
like there's a university in town you go
sweep the floors or whatever you're just
on your honor not to
abscond the justice department was
Furious that the judge ordered that I be
sent to a minimum security Camp so they
arbitrarily just sent me to the regular
prison that was across the street from
the camp and they said that they did
that because I was a trained CIA officer
which made me a national security
threat well if I was a
threat then why don't you send me to a
maximum security penitentiary if you
think I'm so
dangerous so what I ended up doing was I
I ended up um saying yes to every
interview request I ever had Jake Tapper
drove to the prison and interviewed me
for
CNN um I gave multiple interviews to
NPR um ABC News came I mean it was just
count I can't tell you how many Greek
newspapers came I'm a I'm a big star in
Greece because I stood up to the
American government and I I happened to
be a dual us Greek citizen but
um they complained and complained and
complained about all the media contact
that I had and I said listen I'll tell
you guys the honest to God's truth I
told the warden this straight to his
face I said I was told I was going to be
sent to the minimum security Camp across
the street and if I had gone to that
camp you would have never heard about me
I would have just kept my head down I
would have kept my mouth shut I would
have done my 23 months and I would have
gone home but you guys had to be dicks
about it you guys had to make an issue
about it and so I decided that I am
going to exercise my constitutional
rights which I have not given
up to speak with the press and to speak
speak
freely and that's what I did I was a
thorn in their side from the very
beginning just like Marty goddessi is
Daniel's not Daniel just wants to keep
his head down and come home which I
totally respect but for me not a chance
I would ask about the you know the the
the bureaucracy that's able to get away
with these kind of decisions that the
the um you know placing in and I don't
know if this is common for all with
blowers but I assume some form of it is
placing the restrictions on reality
winner as to telling her own story after
she got out of prison yeah now she's
bound to this agreement infinitely you
know I I I guess I wonder about you know
that the the entirely seems you know a l
entire lack of due process and entire
lack of uh equal protection under the
law yeah how how do how are they able to
continue this and and yeah do you feel
that there's big steps that be can be
taken to rectify it in some way oh yeah
reality reality and I have talked about
this her judge seriously overreached by
by infringing on her constitutional
rights I don't think that would stand up
in court for two minutes but she's
afraid to challenge it because they
could technically still send her back to
prison um by violating her they they say
that she uh she broke the terms of her
release and they violate her uh federal
probation and they send her back to
prison so she just wants to get through
it she doesn't want to challenge it when
I got out of prison um they told me that
I had 30 days to find a job or I go back
to prison and so I was offered a job at
a think tank the oldest Progressive
think tank in Washington The Institute
for policy studies and they wanted me to
write about um about uh these these
sentencing reform and judicial reform
and prison reform
issues I said great I took the job and I
had to get permission from the Bureau of
Prisons which is supposed to be proforma
well they denied they denied my request
and they said that it was inappropriate
that Mr kiraku be commenting on Prison
issues so I said you know
what violate me send me
back I'll I'll have every news Network
in America camped out in the prison
parking lot violate me and I took the
job and there was some you know huffing
and puffing but they backed
down um I I think that
reality if if she wanted to uh to
challenge these
Draconian uh
uh Reigns that they have on her ability
to make living and to speak freely and
to talk about her case and herself I
think she would win but but I understand
you know challenging them is not for
everybody so what
um what's to be done you know what if if
if John kiraku had the power today what
would you do to rectify some of this
some of this
stuff uh you got to start from scratch
by tearing down the entire system you
know the
whoever happens to be president at any
given time when it comes time to appoint
a new director of the Bureau of Prisons
they just appoint the same kind of
person one after the other after the
other the current one used to be the
head of the Oregon State Prison System
big deal the the guy before her was the
deputy director of the Bureau of Prisons
the guy before him was a warden and then
the deputy director of the Bureau of
Prisons the guy before him was a general
a brigadier general who was in charge of
the military prison
system well we
need we need fresh thinking fresh ideas
there was a warden in in Maine for
example uh prisoners were complaining
about the quality of food which is not
human grade food it's animal feed grade
food that's fed to prisoners and so the
prison was sitting on this giant you
know 50 acre 100 Acre parcel of property
and so the people who were in the
minimum security he taught them how to
farm and not only now does that prison
is that prison completely
self-sufficient in terms of fruits and
vegetables but they're able to sell
their excess fruits and vegetables in
town that's the kind of thinking that we
need in the prison system now one of the
things that made me very happy uh two
years ago was Hakeem Jeff who's now
the Democratic leader in the House of
Representatives Hakeem Jeff worked with
um Marco
Rubio to push through a
bill that mandated sentencing
reform I I can't stress how how gutsy
that is can you imagine you're you're an
elected member of the House of
Representatives you've got to run for
reelection every two
years and you go out on the camp caign
Trail and you say I'm going to pass a
bill to make it harder to keep people in
prison well how many votes is that going
to win you now that's exactly what needs
to be
done but those two are the only ones
with the balls to actually go out and do
it so we need that kind of bipartisan
legislation let me ask a rhetorical
question too how come the Germans got it
right and the Danes and the swedes and
the Norwegians and the fins you know how
come they got it right how come they
have recidivism rates of 10 and 15% when
ours are
50% why is it the UN declares our
prisons to be sources of torture but
their prisons are set up like
Apartments where you teach people life
skills so that when they go back
out they don't sell drugs and they don't
Rob gas stations and they know how to
you know run a load of laundry and
balance a checkbook because that's what
they're taught to
do so we are uh this the prison system
that we have at every level level you
know city and county state and federal
it's a system that we should be ashamed
of not something that we should hope
others would aspire to ours is an
embarrassment so um my my uh my last
question for you um and this is is kind
kind of kind of similar what we've been
talking about but also kind of different
that
the
um what has been your your observation
of the American um film industry and
television industry in the period for
the global war on te in terms of their
their acquiescence to stories that are
Jive easily with with government
narratives great question uh thank you
for that question um a as a
hobby um ever since 2007 I've been
writing television pilots and I've
actually sold ATM that's amazing awesome
yeah it's been a lot of fun I was the
script advisor on the born ultimatum I
was the script advisor on to Paris With
Love I was the script advisor on um Kill
the Messenger and I was the security
adviser on the kit Runner and I'm just
now we just finished season one I'm the
script adviser on a new show on CBS
that's coming out in February called The
True Lies based on the James Cameron uh
movie of the same of the same so I'm
kind of acquainted with the way these
things play out in Hollywood and I'll
tell you that the easy answer is that
the CIA finally got wise to something
that the FBI learned way back in the 50s
and that's that you have to control the
narrative right have you ever seen a
film not done by Oliver Stone where the
CIA is the bad guy no they don't exist
they don't exist it's gotten to the
point
where um just after the invasion of Iraq
the cia's office of public affairs
opened up a branch inside public affairs
whose sole Duty it is to Lea with
Hollywood
Studios so you want a classified
briefing uh over a classified mockup of
the bin Laden compound Allah zero
dark3 come on and we'll tell you our
side of the story and then that's the
side that you write up as the script for
the movie and we'll give you free access
to the
building right you want to make a movie
that perpetuates the lie that the
torture program resulted in in the the
capture not capture but the killing of
Osama bin Laden that it was torture that
led us to his location you you you want
that lie to be
perpetuated then come on we'll give you
classified briefings and you can
interview the the analysts and do
whatever you want just like in the 50s
the 60s and the early 70s where every
single movie and TV show about the FBI
was Pro FBI because Jay Edgar Hoover had
to approve every single script well now
you've got the CIA that has a hand in
every single script for every movie that
has something to do with the
CIA it's just
wrong something we do pretty frequently
on the podcast is we talk to uh Tom Seer
I don't know if you're familiar with him
he runs spy culture.com
yeah and I think it's one of the most
grotesque aspects of our modern military
industrial complex that they are able to
stick their figures so deeply into what
is otherwise entirely fiction and create
these narratives that absent any other
point of reference people learn a lot
from movies and TV shows sure they do
should they I don't I don't know about
that but they certainly do I know that
the things that I knew about the
military before I joined were all came
from those movies I saw you know the the
rock Blackhawk Down all these you know
different ones um
but that the the enormous power they
have and how how it seems to directly
butt up against any kind of First
Amendment supposed to actually have the
benefit of free speech As Americans one
that extends to filmmakers too and
granted you know there's corporate
interest and other things involved but
you know um listening to a a podcast um
on North Korea recently a uh a director
someone who had uh she had gone to North
Korea and directed a film and she was
talking about comparison of North
Korea's uh desire of involvement with
her film which was almost nonexistent
switched to the American cinematic
landscape where us filmmakers allow huge
changes in their scripts and
presentations in order to receive DOD or
CIA support and it's a blatant active
censorship withholding their support
such as helicopters or other major
equipment and filming locations if the
filmmakers don't properly tow the
government line deciding what can and
can't can't be in the film do this and I
couldn't do this and you know you get
narrowed down into telling a story that
is exactly the story they want told not
anything that is actually controlled by
the filmmaker or can be seen as Truth by
the audience it locks us into these
mindsets of being accepting of violence
as the first solution of being accepting
of seeing American troops in places that
we would you wouldn't think they would
be absolutely right there's never going
to be
a really large change in the Winds of
how America does its foreign policy
until I think until that's rectified in
some more powerful way certainly the top
of whist whistleblowers goes right
alongside that but you know it is it's
what what people run on you know is the
the things you know my wife and I we sit
down every night and we watch new stuff
but now we understand that we're not
just dealing with the desires and and
whims of filmmakers and writers and
things like that we're dealing with them
literally having being military or
intelligence I wouldn't call them
overlords overseers I guess would be a
better way to put it to say this is okay
and this is not okay um and it's and
it's it's just disgusting I had another
experience with a buddy who um you know
the uh the National Geographic series
The Long Road Hope sure A friend of mine
who deployed to Baghdad in early 2004
his unit saw action during early April
that year that was portrayed in the Long
Road Home I traveled to his home in New
York and together we watched that and we
recorded some of his responses from it
and just to see you know just basic
things that were just not right
pretending that there were suicide
bombers in Kosovo was one that I I that
I could never just oh man that made me
so angry oh
yes but
um anyway I think that's probably a good
place for us to wrap it up for today you
asked very smart questions very very
OnPoint questions so thank you for that
I would ask one favor if if anybody's
interested in these issues I just
migrated over to substack it's John
kiraku Dos substack
docomo I I really enjoyed it too John I
am I am actually a new uh a new
subscriber to your substack I've really
enjoyed it so far and uh I hope to have
you back sometime I look forward to that
thanks very much for
all right thanks John and uh thank you
everyone for listening today we'll we'll
catch you next time take care money is
tight these days for everyone penny
pinching to make it through the month
often doesn't give people the funds to
contribute to a Creator they support so
we consider it the highest honor that
folks help us fund the podcast in any
dollar amount they're able patreons is
the main place to do that and for
supporters who can donate $10 a month
more they will be listed right here as
an honorary producer like these fine
folks fim sherazi James Oar James
Higgins Eric Phillips Paul Appel Julie
Dupri Thomas Benson Janet Hansen Daniel
Fleming Michael Karen Ren Jacob Howard
Reynolds Rick coffee Scott Spalding
Spooky Tooth and the status quo
podcast however if patreon isn't your
style you can contribute directly
through PayPal at
paypal.me fortress on a hill or please
check out our store on spreadshirt for
some great Fortress
merch we're on Twitter and facebook.com
at Fortress onah Hill you can find our
full collection of episodes at ww
Fortress onah
hill.com skepticism is One's best armor
never never forget it we'll see you next
[Music]
time come
on you good
[Music]
people and listen to my
song I
hope you'll pay
attention I will not detain you
long